Register of the King Petar II Karadordevic miscellaneous papers, 1943-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
King Petar II Karađorđevic' miscellaneous papers,
1943-1974
74092
Petar II Karađorđevic', King of Yugoslavia, 1923-1970.
1 folder, 6 phonorecords (0.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence and announcements, relating to the Yugoslav exile government during World War II, resistance movements in occupied Yugoslavia, politics and government, and Yugoslav emigre politics. Photocopy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence and announcements, relating to the Yugoslav exile government during World War II, resistance movements in occupied Yugoslavia, politics and government, and Yugoslav emigre politics. Photocopy.
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavs in foreign countries.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Court and courtiers.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Yugoslavia--Politics and government.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Carol, King of Romania (Box 1.)
  - Churchill, Winston
  - Eden, Anthony
  - Gavrilo, Patriarch of the Serbian Orthodox Church
  - George IV, King of England
  - Officers, non-commissioned officers, and soldiers
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
  - Truman, Harry S
  - Vukovich-Bircanin, Momcilo
  - Miscellaneous
- Subject File
  - "Announcement," from the office of His Majesty King Peter II, London, 1956 June 10 (in Serbian) (Box 1.)
  - Christmas Greeting, by King Peter II, Cannes, 1967 December 21 (in Serbian)
  - Open Letter, "Dear Brother Serbs," from the Heir Apparent Crown Prince Alexander Karadjordjevich, London, 1974 (in Serbian)
- Sound recordings (phonorecords)
  - Sound recording of King Peter II luncheon on Yugoslav Liberty Day, 1941 September 6 (Record cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 74092_a_0001772
    Yugoslav Liberty Day luncheon at the Commodore Hotel in New York in celebration of King Peter II's 18th birthday. Several speeches are made decrying the Nazi aggression in Europe in opposition to liberty.3 discs
  - Sound recording of address by King Peter II of Yugoslavia, 1942 June 26 (Record cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 74092_a_0001773
    King Peter II speaks to the American people from a Washington, D.C. studio. He holds that America is a beacon of liberty for the people of Yugoslavia. He then details the defense of Yugoslavia against the Nazi invasion, including the military leaders still in the country commanding the Yugoslav forces. Concluding, he speaks to people of Yugoslavian descent in his native language. Audio says this program was presented by the Blue Network. Concluding side has NBC chimes. 2 discs